So we now continue on today's דף daf is י"ג, Yud Gimmel,
we're continuing on the bottom of י"ב עמוד ב'. Yud Bet Amud
Bet. We just read the משנה Mishnah and we had a debate
about how you about the if you eat food over a period
of time, a כזית, kezayit, when does it combine? And רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir said like eating nuts. So what does it mean? איבעיא
להו, Iba'ya lehu, says the גמרא, Gemara, about eight lines from the
bottom, they asked: רבי מאיר לחומרא קאמר או לקולא קאמר? Rabbi Meir
lechumra ka'amar o lekula ka'amar?
Is he being strict
or lenient, excuse me. לחומרא קאמר, Lechumra ka'amar, is he being strict?
והכי קתני, Vehachi katani, and this is what he's teaching: כאילו אוכל
קליות, Ke'ilu ochel kelayot,
like somebody eating nuts, דאפילו כולי יומא, de'afillu kulo yoma, that even
if they're eating the entire day, ואף על גב דמתחילה ועד סוף
יותר מכדי אכילת פרס, ve'af al gav demitchila ve'ad sof yoter mikedei
achilat pras, even though it's more than the time it takes to
eat a פרס, pras, כיון דמשכי אכילתה, kivan demashchei achilata,
since it's stretching out, מחייב, mechayav, you're liable. So what does it
mean? How is eating nuts mean the entire day? So the way
Rashi's a little unclear, the way רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom explains this
is that what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying is continuous eating.
Now, right, meaning you're constantly eating and chewing and one thing immediately
follows the next, and he says it's combined by continuous eating. Now
that could be a stringency, as long as you're eating continuously, even
if it takes you the whole day, right? So you could be
chewing, chewing, chewing, chewing a quarter of a כזית kezayit and then
you put the next little bit in, as long as you're eating
continuously, even if it's the entire day, it will combine.
So that's what he means, קליות kelayot
means eating yeah, like eat one nut right after the next, like
eating those sunflower seeds, right? One pops out right in your hand,
in your mouth right after the next. So clearly that's what it
means, continuous. But it's חומרא chumra if you say continuous and therefore
no matter how long it lasts as long as it's continuous. Okay,
and then the אמרו לו רבנן, amru lo rabanan, the Rabbis say
to him, עד שיהא בכדי אכילת פרס הוא דחייב יותר מכדי אכילת
פרס פטור. ad she'yehei bekedei achilat pras hu dechayav yoter mikedei achilat
pras patur.
I'm sorry, I don't care continuous or not continuous, it only goes
by כדי אכילת פרס kedei achilat pras and not more. או דלמא
לקולא קאמר, Od dilma lekula ka'amar, maybe he's being lenient? דהכי קתני,
Dehachi katani,
this is what he's saying: כאילו אוכל קליות והוא דלא פסק ביני
וביני, Ke'ilu ochel kelayot vehu delo pasak beinei ubeinei,
that it's only if it's continuous, there's no break, אבל פסק ביני
וביני, aval pasak beinei ubeinei, if there's a break, אף על גב
דמתחילה ועד סוף בכדי אכילת פרס, af al gav demitchila ve'ad sof
bekedei achilat pras, פטור, patur,
you're exempt. ואמרו ליה רבנן, Ve'amru lei rabanan, כיון דמתחילה ועד סוף
בכדי אכילת פרס הוא, kivan demitchila ve'ad sof bekedei achilat pras hu,
חייב. chayav.
And they say it doesn't matter, as long as it's אכילת פרס
achilat pras you're חייב. chayav. Which means what? Again, I'm reading this
right like רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, it means that he agrees to
the principle of אכילת פרס achilat pras and in addition to אכילת
פרס achilat pras he adds the criteria only if there's no break,
right? So then it's a big leniency, the only way it combines,
unless you're talking about eating מצה matzah on סדר Seder night, the
only way it combines is both it's אכילת פרס, achilat pras, that
amount of time, plus there's no break. And the Rabbis say it's
all about the time, it's not about the break.
You have to eat a
כזית בכדי אכילת פרס kezayis bichdei achilas pras.
and it only if it's also continuous. And the Rabbis say it
only goes by the time. So is he saying continuous regardless of
time, or is he saying continuous in addition to a time limit
of כדי אכילת פרס? kedei achilat pras? Okay, that's the way רבינו
גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom explains the question.
תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. What? This is why תוספות
Tosafot says is הפסק, ifsik, because the whole thing here is הפסק
ifsik also?
Yeah, yeah, so רש"י Rashi we just eat it, I'm not going
to get into that. Okay, anyway, okay, תא שמע, Ta shema, come
and hear. וחכמים אומרים עד שיהא בכדי אכילת פרס מתחילה ועד
סוף. Vachachamim omrim ad she'yehei bekedei achilat pras mitchila ve'ad sof. Until
you until it until you go from אכילת פרס achilat pras from
beginning to end. Top of י"ג עמוד א'. Yud Gimmel Amud Aleph.
אי אמרת בשלמא Iy amart bishlama רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir לחומרא, lechumra,
if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was being strict and saying it could
go the whole day if you were eating continuously, היינו דקתני עד
שיהא. hainu de'katani ad she'yehei. So then the Rabbis are saying back,
no, once it's more than
it's only until כדי אכילת פרס. kedei achilat pras. More than that
doesn't combine. So עד, ad, right, is making a limit. You want
to go that far? No, we're going to limit it to כדי
אכילת פרס. kedei achilat pras. עד שיהא בכדי אכילת פרס, Ad she'yehei
bekedei achilat pras, until his
only up to the point that the break is that the duration
is אכילת פרס. achilat pras. More than that it will not combine.
So that's what it means, only until that point will it combine.
And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir presumably saying even longer. אלא אי אמרת
Ela iy amart רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir לקולא, lekula, if רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is being lenient, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says not
only is there אכילת פרס achilat pras but it has to be
continuous, then the Rabbis should not say oh it combines only until
a פרס. pras. They should say חכמים אומרים אם שהה מיבעי ליה,
chachamim omrim im sheha miba'ei lei, as long as you waited that
time regardless of whether it was continuous or not, that's enough. So
אלא לאו שמע מינה רבי מאיר לחומרא שמע מינה. ela lav shema
mina Rabbi Meir lechumra shema mina.
So from here it's very clear, since the Rabbis say you're only
חייב chayav when it goes up to a פרס, pras, it means
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was saying you're חייב chayav even a
longer period of time. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says continuous no
matter how long it takes, and the Rabbis say no, it's always
limited by כדי אכילת פרס. kedei achilat pras. So now we've clarified
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now let's go on. אמר רבנאי אמר שמואל,
Amar Ravannai amar Shmuel, רבנאי Ravannai said in the name of שמואל,
Shmuel, בחלבים ובנבילות עד שיהא מתחילה ועד סוף בכדי אכילת פרס, bechalavim
uveneveilot ad she'yehei mitchila ve'ad sof bekedei achilat pras, like we said,
when it comes to forbidden foods like חלב chelev or נבילה. neveilah.
So נבילה neveilah by the way is not a חטאת, chatat, although
that's our subject,
נבילה neveilah would be lashes. But the point is when it comes
to any איסור issur forbidden foods, it goes from כדי אכילת פרס
kedei achilat pras from the beginning to the end. Again, simple says
the beginning to the end is from the beginning of the eating
to the end of the eating, although
תוספות... Tosafot... Now, אוכלים טמאים, ochlim tmeiyim, שקצים ורמשים, shkatzim u'remasim, ומשקים,
u'mashkim, אפילו כל היום כולו, afilu kol hayom kulo, בכדי אכילת פרס.
bekedei achilat pras However, when it comes to to to a טמא
tamei food, תוספות Tosafos brackets some of these things in here which
are also non-kosher foods. The emphasis is טמא tamei food, then even
if it takes you the whole day, as long as it's בכדי
אכילת פרס. bichdei achilas pras. Now that's a pretty bizarre statement. Even
if it takes you the whole day as long as it's בכדי...
what does that mean? Now the first thing you have to know,
and I skipped over this in the משנה, Mishnah is that when
you eat non-normally, you have a non-kosher food, it is let... not
non-kosher, a טמא tamei food, it could be like a שני, sheini,
okay, his second degree of טומאה, tumah, or even if it's a
ראשון. rishon. The only way a person becomes טמא tamei is if
he touches an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. You cannot become טמא tamei
from touching a ראשון rishon or a שני. sheini. So normally if
you touch this טמא tamei food, you're not טמא, tamei, but חז"ל
Chazal said if you eat it, you do become טמא. tamei. It's
rabbinic. Only if you eat though not a כזית, kezayit but half
of a פרס, pras, which basically would be like four זיתים zeisim
according to or maybe four and a half depending on how big
a פרס pras is. Okay, so if you eat four כזיתים kezaysim
of this non-kosher... not non-kosher, of this טמא tamei food, you become
טמא. tamei. So now you're going to understand what it means. It
says you can eat it the whole day as long as you
eat כזית בכדי אכילת פרס. kezayis bichdei achilas pras. So let's see
what that means.
גמרא, Gemara, יוסף בר... Yosef bar...
this is yeah, because this is about טומאה. tumah. So גמרא Gemara
says מאי קאמר, mai kama, what does this mean? אמר רב פפא
הכי קאמר, amar Rav Pappa hachi kama, this is what it means.
אפילו כל היום כולו, afilu kol hayom kulo, you can even if
you eat this טמא tamei food over the entire day you'll become
טמא, tamei, והוא שאכל כזית כזית, vehu she'achal kezayis kezayis,
there's an extra word כזית kezayis, here that shouldn't be here, it's
as long as you eat each כזית בכדי אכילת פרס. kezayis bichdei
achilas pras, Meaning, as we said, how much you have to eat
to become טמא? tamei? Four כזיתים. kezaysim. So if each כזית kezayis
you eat within, you know, בכדי אכילת פרס, bichdei achilas pras. whatever
that is, four minutes or whatever, then even if you ate one
כזית kezayis at 9:00 AM, one at 12:00 PM, one at 2:00,
one at 3:00 PM, and one at 5:00 PM, as long as
each individual כזית kezayis was בכדי אכילת פרס, bichdei achilas pras, they
combine. Which is a little strange because you would think once you're
in the category of a larger amount and it's making you טמא,
tamei, it's about viewing that entire thing as one eating, as one
פרס. pras. You know,
and part of this I would say is a question of conceptually,
do we look at eating as an act or as a process?
Okay, so maybe that's what it's saying, that, you know, when it's
eating four כזית kezayis worth, that's a large amount, that we look
at as a process. It's a process that can take place over
the whole day. Okay, but the process is made up of individual
acts of eating, and each act of eating is the כזית. kezayis
So if each... if you ate less than a כזית בכדי אכילת
פרס, kezayis bichdei achilas pras, then it's not considered like an act
of eating at all. So if you have an act of eating
כזית בכדי אכילת פרס, kezayis bichdei achilas pras, then different distinct acts
can combine to be seen as a process, but each one has
to be an act in itself. Something like that.
And benching in between still מצטרף? mitztaref?
Presumably, yeah. Because it's not about benching, it's about טומאה tumah and
that goes by... that's an interesting point, you know, doesn't benching itself
also make an end? That's a good point. Anyway, but let's take
a look. So גמרא Gemara says like this. That anyway, so that's
an interesting idea about becoming טמא, tamei, that it's a concept of
כזית kezayis. בכדי אכילת פרס, bichdei achilas pras, but also a concept
of more than a כזית. kezayis. מיתיבי. meisivei. Now that was the
statement. Now let's see if it's really true. כל האוכלים מצטרפין לפסול
את הגוייה בכחצי פרס. kol ha'ochlim mitztarfin lifsol es hagviyah b'chatzi pras.
So this is a משנה Mishna in מקואות, Mikvaos, that all foods,
טמא tamei foods, combine to make the body טמא, tamei, meaning if
you eat them, if you eat a half of a פרס, pras,
four זיתים. zeisim. מאי לאו דאכלי לחצי פרס בכדי אכילת פרס? mai
lav d'achlei l'chatzi pras bichdei achilas pras?
Presumably it means you ate that amount in the time of בכדי
אכילת פרס, bichdei achilas pras, which actually by the way, it means
you have to eat even quicker than normal because now you have
to eat four כזיתים kezaysim in the time of בכדי אכילת פרס,
bichdei achilas pras, not just one
כזית. kezayis. גמרא Gemara says לא דאכל כזית כזית בכדי אכילת פרס.
lo d'achal kezayis kezayis bichdei achilas pras. No, it means it would
be a case that you ate each כזית kezayis within the בכדי
אכילת פרס, bichdei achilas pras, but the כזיתים kezaysim themselves could be
spread out throughout the day. And what's the חצי פרס chatzi pras
then? חצי פרס chatzi pras is the size of how much, that's
why I've been saying four כזיתים. kezaysim. א פרס a pras is
about eight כזיתים. kezaysim. So חצי פרס chatzi pras is the amount
of טמא tamei food that makes you טמא. tamei. Okay. So גמרא
Gemara says, מיתיבי, meisivei, I'll ask you. כל האוכלים מצטרפין לפסול את
הגוייה בכחצי פרס בכדי אכילת פרס. kol ha'ochlim mitztarfin lifsol es hagviyah
b'chatzi pras bichdei achilas pras.
Over here you have a ברייתא braisa that is explicit, that you
have to eat half of a פרס, pras, meaning four כזיתים, kezaysim,
in the time of בכדי אכילת פרס. bichdei achilas pras. And now
the ברייתא braisa goes on to say what that time means. כיצד?
keitzad? אכל וחזר ואכל. achal v'chazar v'achal.
If you ate and then you ate again. אם יש מתחילה עד
תחילה ראשונה, im yesh mit'chilah ad t'chilah rishonah,
pretty explicit, from the beginning of the first eating, עד סוף אכילה
אחרונה, ad sof achilah achronah, till the end of the last eating,
בכדי אכילת פרס, bichdei achilas pras, the time of אכילת פרס, achilas
pras, מצטרפין, mitztarfin, יותר מכאן אין מצטרפין. yoseir mikan ein mitztarfin. So
if it's within אכילת פרס achilas pras it combines to make you
טמא, tamei, more than that it does not combine. לא התירו לאכול
פחות מכשיעור לירד ולטבול. lo hitiru le'echol pachus mikeshiur lereid v'litvol.
If you ate less than that amount, they didn't allow you go
to the מקוה. mikvah. So that's a bizarre statement. Who cares about
going to the מקוה? mikvah? We'll worry about that later. ירד וטבל,
yarad v'taval, if you went to the מקוה, mikvah, ועלה והשלימו, v'alah
v'hishlimo,
let's say you ate two כזיתים kezaysim of טמא tamei food, then
you went to the מקוה, mikvah, and then you came up and
you ate another two כזיתים kezaysim of this
food, מצטרף. mitztaref. You are still טמא. tamei. Having gone to the
מקוה mikvah having gone to the מקוה mikvah in the middle does
not prevent you from becoming טמא tamei because when you went to
the מקוה mikvah. you weren't yet טמא. tamei. Okay, so
the going to the מקוה mikvah. does not break it up. Okay,
so התירו לעוברה, hitiru la'ubara, they allowed a pregnant woman לאכול פחות
מכשיעור, le'echol pachos mikishiur, to eat less than a שיעור shiur because
of סכנה. sakana. Now who cares? I mean, it's only about טומאה.
tumah. What does that mean anyway? So anyway, we'll worry about that.
כל המשקין מצטרפין לשית לגביה ברביעית. kol hamashkin mitztarfin l'shis l'gviya b'reviis.
Now food is a half of a פרס, pras, four כזיתים. kezaisim.
If it's liquid, טמא tamei liquid, how much does that make you
טמא? tamei? It's a רביעית. reviis. And now you have to drink
the רביעית. reviis. The רביעית reviis is like what the minimum size
for a קידוש kiddush cup, it's about three and a half ounces.
Now you have to drink that בכדי אכילת פרס, b'chedei achilas pras,
the time it takes you of בכדי אכילת פרס. k'dei achilas pras.
כיצד? keitzad? שתה וחזר ושתה, shasa v'chazar v'shasa, you drank and then
you drank again. אם יש מתחילת שתייה ראשונה ועד סוף שתייה אחרונה,
im yesh mitechilas shtiya rishona v'ad sof shtiya achrona, from the beginning
of the first one till the end of the last one, בכדי
אכילת פרס, k'dei achilas pras, the time of אכילת פרס achilas pras
מצטרף, mitztaref, it combines. יותר מכאן אין מצטרף, yoser mikan ein mitztaref,
more than that it does not combine. So anyway, this is a
very long ברייתא. braisa. We're going to look at each part, but
so far we're quite explicit that when it comes to טומאה, tumah,
it you do not have the whole day. You have from the
beginning of the of the beginning, from the beginning of the first
eating or drinking to the end of the last one, the entire
time is בכדי אכילת פרס. k'dei achilas pras. You do not have
more than that.
So they're using a שיעור shiur for drinking that's one for eating.
I know.
So yeah, that is true. We're not going to overanalyze that. That
gets more analyzed in like the גמרא gemara in נזיר nazir and
other places. Okay, anyway, so it just ends with הותרו לה למגע
טמא להניק בנה, hutru lo l'maga tamei l'hanik b'nah,
they allowed a woman who is טמא מת, tmei meis, who had
touched a corpse, so she's a ראשון, rishon, to nurse her child,
ובנה טהור, u'vnah tahor, and her child is טהור. tahor. Because if
a if a person is a who touches a מת meis is
a ראשון, rishon, she's touching her child, her child is a a
person doesn't become a שני sheini by being touched by a ראשון.
rishon. A person can only become טמא tamei by touching an אב.
av. Now the question is why doesn't the milk make the child
טמא? tamei? Because that obviously that's the context here. So right, so
so we'll talk about that. Anyway, so we're going to have a
lot of fun analyzing this ברייתא, braisa, but first we're going to
talk about our focus. קתני מיהת, katani mi'at, nevertheless, meaning the focus
right now is אם יש מתחילת אכילה ראשונה ועד סוף אכילה בכדי
אכילת פרס מצטרף. im yesh mitechilas achila rishona v'ad sof achila b'chedei
achilas pras mitztaref.
It's from the beginning to the end of the eating process is
אכילת פרס, achilas pras, it combines. So you do not have a
whole day to do it. תיובתא דרבנא תיובתא. tiyuvta d'rabbana tiyuvta.
So that completely contradicts רבנא. rabbana. You you see here that even
when it comes to טומאה, tumah, and even though the amount is
more than a כזית, kezayis, even if the amount goes up to
four כזיתים kezaisim because it's the amount that makes you טמא, tamei,
you still the only period to combine is בכדי אכילת פרס. k'dei
achilas pras. Now that is bizarre, right? Because you would have thought
that if it's four כזיתים, kezaisim, you have four times as much.
Similar like if it's a רביעית, reviis, you would have said it's
בכדי שתיית רביעית, b'chedei shtiyas reviis, not בכדי אכילת פרס. b'chedei achilas
pras. And sometimes we do say בכדי שתיית רביעית. b'chedei shtiyas reviis.
So again, that's like a fascinating question which gets more analyzed in
other גמרא, gemara, why are these some type of weird hybrid? But
for our immediate purposes, we see though that you do not have
the whole day. It has to be the same type of a
act, not a process, or if it's a process, more well-defined as
בכדי אכילת פרס. b'chedei achilas pras. I should also say, going back
to the point I said before, this seems quite explicit that בכדי
אכילת פרס b'chedei achilas pras is not the measure of the break,
right? I don't see, I don't think how you could be more
explicit. From the beginning of the first eating to the end of
the last eating is the time of the entire period. So it
is interesting that a previous תוספות tosfos and, for example, I'll give
you an example on יום כיפור. yom kippur. Right now, of course,
we try to be מחמיר, machmir, but normally if somebody is sick
and not sick enough that they, you know, it's not enough, it's
enough
to allow them to eat, but they eat less than a שיעור
shiur each time or drink, you normally define the amount of time
that you have to break between, right? Somebody will, the rabbi will
say, well, wait x number of minutes, depending on which rabbi you
ask, four minutes, nine minutes, fifteen minutes, eight, wait x number of
minutes, you know, between the sips of orange juice that you're taking
or whatever the case might be. Okay, so but you know, now
of course, again, this גמרא gemara makes it very clear that we
are doing from the beginning of the process to the end of
the process. People that go crazy, for example, on the other flip
side of eating מצה, matzah, right? I don't know if you've ever
encountered one of these guys that, you know, has to be מחמיר.
machmir. First you have a huge definition of what a שיעור shiur
of a כזית kezayis is, and then you have to get it
all in in two minutes. So some people say like you're not
even יוצא yotzei that way, it's אכילה גסה. achila gassa. There's another
interesting question I would also say, which is אכילת פרס achilas pras
a function of the food you're eating? So if you were to
say that this much, this amount of מצה matzah is כזית, kezayis,
then it would be not the time it would take me to
eat four כזיתים kezaisim of bread, it would be the time it
would take me to eat four כזיתים kezaisim of מצה. matzah. Or
do you not say that? Do you always go by a standard
regardless of what you're eating? Okay, but anyway, so those are all
important questions of בכדי אכילת פרס. b'chedei achilas pras. But anyway, there
the people that are stuffing it down are measuring from the beginning
of the eating to the end. They're not taking breaks, right? So
they're not measuring a space of a break, they're measuring the beginning
to the end. So there are those two ideas out there and
we tend to be מחמיר machmir both ways, depending on the case,
whether the measurement is the time of the entire process or the
time of the break. But certainly this גמרא... gemara... גמרא Gemara makes
it quite clear, even the language of the משנה Mishnah was pretty
clear, but this makes it explicit that it's the measure of the
entire process, not the measure of the break. Okay, so now let's
look at the very beginning of how we'll do that, right? Because
yes, but but often what we do is you know when we're
concerned people tend to be מחמיר machmir both ways. So if you're
trying to be יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah and get it you're
trying to get it בכדי אכילת פרס, b'khdei akhilat pras, you're going
to measure the shorter time, the entire process. If you're trying to
get out of בכדי אכילת פרס, b'khdei akhilat pras, like drinking little
bits on יום כיפור Yom Kippur when there's a need, then you're
measuring the break, you're being מחמיר machmir the opposite direction. Okay, but
again, the simple sense is that it doesn't matter, it's always the
entire process. Let's go back to the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, אמר מר, Amar Mar, let's look at the ברייתא.
Braita. לא התירו לו לאכול פחות מכשיעור לירד ולטבול. Lo hitiru lo
le'ekhol pakhos mikishiur lereid velidbol. If you ate less than a שיעור
shiur to make you טמא, tamei, they did not let you go
down to the מקוה. mikvah? If you ate let's say only two
כזיתים, kezaysim, go to the מקוה. mikvah מאי קאמר, Mai kama, what
does that mean? Who cares if you go to the מקוה? mikvah
Go to the hate. So אמר רב יהודה הכי קאמר. Amar Rav
Yehuda hakhi kama. אכל פחות מכשיעור, Akhal pakhos mikishiur, if you ate
less than a שיעור, shiur, לא התירו לו לירד ולטבול. lo hitiru
lo lereid velidbol. Here they didn't want you to go to the
מקוה mikvah after eating two כזיתים. kezaysim. Why not? שאם ירד וטבל
ועלה, She'im yarad vetaval ve'ala, because if you went to the מקוה
mikvah, and came up, והשלימו, vehishlimo, and you ate the next two
כזיתים, kezaysim, מצטרף, mitztaref, then it will combine and you will become
טמא. tamei. But you're not going to think you're טמא tamei
because you will have thought that having gone to the מקוה mikvah
sort of stops the process, like Michael thought בדיקה bedika stops the
process, so you'll have a reason, well I went to the מקוה,
mikvah it can't be part of a process up to a, I
went to the מקוה mikvah in the middle. ואתי למימר, Ve'asi lemeimar,
you'll say, הני לטבילה כמעליא, hani letevila kema'alya, going to the מקוה
mikvah helped, ואינו יודע, ve'eino yodeia, you don't know the הלכה, halakha,
שאין טבילה אלא באחרונה, she'ein tevila ela ba'akhrona, that going to the
מקוה mikvah, is only meaningful after you're טמא, tamei, before you're טמא
tamei it's not meaningful and it doesn't interrupt the process, and therefore
they did not want you to go to the מקוה mikvah in
between because then you will come to be lenient and think you
are not טמא. tamei. Now I should by the way point out
that this has got to be a pretty quick... yeah, I was
thinking now that we're saying that from the very beginning to the
end is בכדי אכילת פרס, b'khdei akhilat pras, okay, so you're eating
it in the מקוה, mikvah you jump in, jump out, but okay,
anyway, fine. Okay, so that's that idea, they don't want you to
go because going to the מקוה will not break up the process
and you will be confused. Now let's look at the next case.
קתני, Katani, התירו לעוברת, hitiru la'uberet, they let a pregnant woman לאכול
פחות מכשיעור מפני הסכנה, le'ekhol pakhos mikishiur mipnei hasakana, because of cases
of סכנה sakana like there's a concern that you know danger to
the pregnancy.
מעוברת Me'uberet then. עוברת, Uberet, yeah, עוברת uberet is a way of
saying מעוברת. me'uberet. מפני הסכנה, Mipnei hasakana, if she's in danger, אפילו
טובא נמי תאכל, afilu tuva nami tekhol, let her eat a lot,
who cares? Right, do whatever you want, if I'm not whatever you
want, but you know what I'm saying, if it's danger it allows
you to do what's necessary. אמר רב פפא הכי קתני, Amar Rav
Papa hakhi katani, this is what it means. הותרה לעוברת פחות מכשיעור
אפילו טובא. Hutra la'uberet pakhos mikishiur afilu tuva. They allowed a pregnant
woman to eat less than a שיעור shiur even if she did
it many many many less than a שיעור. shiur. And this is
interesting because the question is like where do we get this concept,
and I'm not going to fully elaborate on this, but where do
we get this concept of פחות פחות מכשיעור, pakhos pakhos mikishiur, like
they say on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Like make up your mind,
if it's not a סכנה sakana then it doesn't allow anything, but
if it is a סכנה sakana it should allow me to eat
even as much as is necessary. Which of course we say if
there's a real סכנה. sakana. Where do we get this idea that
there's like a middle category where it's a quasi-סכנה, sakana, not really
a סכנה, sakana, but it's enough to allow you to eat פחות
מכשיעור? pakhos mikishiur? Well that idea is, although here it's about טומאה
tumah and it's not about non-kosher food, but you have at least
the model of that idea here because here it says that they
allowed this pregnant woman to eat many half amounts, even you know
eat half amounts many many times, even though the total she ate
a hundred half amounts but they'll all have been distinct and separate
so they don't combine. Okay, so here you actually have the model
of that. Now of course again you could still ask the same
question, if it's a real סכנה sakana you wouldn't have to do
half measures, you could do full measures. So the גמרא Gemara never
really fully answers that question, but it's saying if for some reason
you're able to get away with it by doing half measures over
a period of time, then you go ahead and do that. Okay,
so לאכול פחות מכשיעור מפני הסכנה. le'ekhol pakhos mikishiur mipnei hasakana. So
I'm sorry, the גמרא Gemara says לעוברת פחות מכשיעור אפילו טובא, la'uberet
pakhos mikishiur afilu tuva, many many half שיעורים shiurim they allowed her
מפני הסכנה. mipnei hasakana. Okay, קתני, Katani, התירו למגע טמא מת. hitiru
lemaga tamei meit. Now by the way the question is you know
what's the... I should also point out that what's the big deal
that she became טמא? tamei? I mean why don't you just let
her become טמא? tamei? What does that have to do with סכנה?
sakana? If she becomes טמא, tamei, who's to hate? So תוספות Tosafot
says the case is is that let's say that she's going to
have to eat תרומה, terumah, like the only available food is תרומה
terumah and after you finish feeding her this stuff she's going to
have to eat תרומה, terumah, so you're making her טמא tamei and
therefore ultimately it's going to lead to her eating תרומה terumah which
is going to be a necessary thing. But again it's very bizarre
because since in this act itself you're not you know it's not
a sin, you're just making her טמא tamei in this act, why
do you have to do these half measures? So that's like never
fully clarified, you know this explanation of half measures, yes.
There's an Artscroll footnote that says רמבן Ramban holds even if she
ate a large amount of food in order to avoid danger she
does not have to immerse in a מקוה before eating תרומה terumah
because she is considered טהור. tahor.
If you do it by half measures, right. So that's exactly the...
So the point though, meaning, but it gets back to the question,
we have to say מפני הסכנה, mipnei hasakana, as long as you're
doing it by half measures and there's a break more than כדי
אכילת פרס, k'dei achilat pras, forget מפני הסכנה, mipnei hasakana, there's no
איסור issur to become
טמא. tamei. Right, so it's not clear at all sort of why
the גמרא, Gemara, A, why you need both of these, once it's
סכנה sakana why you know, anyway, so the whole answer about the
mumbas is not clear at all. A, there's no איסור issur of
becoming
טמא, tamei, B, why do you need מפני הסכנה mipnei hasakana since
it's פחות מכשיעור pachos mik'shiur anyway. All right, but that's that case.
And also what איסור issur is she doing which תוספות Tosafot has
to throw in that there's תרומה Terumah somewhere around. Let's move on.
Now this is something the גמרא Gemara now gets very involved in
is the case of the pregnant woman feeding her child.
קתני: Katani: התירו למגע טמאי מת להניק את בנה. Hitiru l'maga t'mei
meit l'hanik et b'nah. They allowed a woman who touched a corpse,
so she- I'm sorry, is it למגע טמאי מת? l'maga t'mei meit?
One second, excuse me. Yeah, למגע טמאי מת. l'maga t'mei meit. So
she touched somebody, no, that would make her a שני, sheni, but
she's not a שני sheni because hold on one second.
Oh no no, I'm right, that's right, right. If you touch a
corpse, I'm sorry, I said it wrong before. Right, the מת meit
is the אבי אבות הטומאה, avi avot hatumah, the person who touches
a corpse is an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. So she touched a
person who touched a corpse, so she's a ראשון. rishon. Okay, yeah,
I think I skipped the middle step
there. Okay, so they allowed למגע טמאי מת, l'maga t'mei meit, if
she touched somebody who touched a corpse, so she's a ראשון, rishon,
להניק את בנה, l'hanik et b'nah, to nurse her child, ובנה טהור,
u'vnah tahor, and the child is טהור. tahor. Now she, because she's
only a ראשון, rishon, because she's touched the guy who touched the
מת, meit, she's only ראשון, rishon, her touch does not make her
son or her daughter, whatever, her child טמא, tamei, because a person
can only be a ראשון, rishon, cannot be lower. But the question
is why does her milk not make it that the infant is
drinking טמא tamei milk and therefore making him טמא? tamei? So let's
take a look. אמאי טהור? Amai tahor? Why is the infant טהור?
tahor? כיון דינק חלב, Keivan d'yanak chalav, since he's nursing milk, אטמי
ליה מחלב, itmi lei meichalav, he becomes טמא tamei through the milk.
וכי תימא לא הוכשר, V'chi teima lo huchshar, maybe the milk has
not become הוכשר. huchshar. Now you remember, not הכשר hechsher like an
OU. Anyway, you remember the idea is with טומאה tumah that food
does not become טמא tamei until after it comes in contact with
a liquid, okay? So that's the principle of הכשר זרעים hechsher z'raim
or הוכשר huchshar and so on. Now of course the problem is
that milk is itself a liquid. Who needs it to come in
contact with liquid? So the interesting point is,
is this still inside of her?
No, the גמרא Gemara says, if I'm let's say like, you know
the שבת Shabbos הלכה halacha for example, I can squeeze my lemon
onto my fish, right, but I can't squeeze it into the water,
because a liquid going into a food is considered a food. Going
into itself or into a liquid is a liquid. So here what
רש"י Rashi says is, we consider milk a food, not a liquid.
Why? He never really fully explains it, but I think what he
means is as far as the infant is
concerned, although in terms of the physical qualities of it it's a
liquid, this is not a drink, this is the food of the
infant. So רש"י Rashi makes an analogy to this גמרא Gemara about
if it's being squeezed into food it's food, and רש"י Rashi says
here too, mother's milk for an infant is considered food, not a
liquid. Okay, therefore because it's a food it needs to come in
contact with liquid to become able to become טמא. tamei. If it
were a liquid it naturally would become טמא, tamei, but if we
conceptualize it as food, then it is not susceptible to becoming טמא
tamei until it comes in contact with liquid.
But it does come in contact, right? Because it's the saliva of
the infant or something like that?
So we'll get there. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, so, וכי
תימא לא הוכשר, v'chi teima lo huchshar,
if you say that it did not become susceptible because of coming
טמא, tamei, no, הוכשר בטיפה מלוכלכת על פי הדד. nuchshar b'tipa m'luchlechet
al pi hadad.
There is the sort of soiled drop of milk on the breast,
meaning that not all the milk goes into the infant, some of
it remains on the mother, and therefore that which is not going
to end up in the infant's belly is not food but liquid.
And that liquid touches the milk that is going into the infant's
belly and makes that considered to be susceptible for טומאה. tumah. So
אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah
bar Avuha, so anyway that's the question, so why isn't this milk
טמא tamei and that makes the infant טמא? tamei? So אמר רב
נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah bar Avuha,
שינק בתקיפה אחת ולא הניח טיפה מלוכלכת על פי הדד. she-yanak b'tkifa
achat v'lo hiniach tipa m'luchlechet al pi hadad. So he basically he
nursed with one grabbing on, in one sort of immediate, quick process,
and therefore it never sort of left, his mouth never detached, and
therefore the drop of milk never got onto the breast and therefore
it never made the milk that was going into his stomach fit.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבה שתי תשובות בדבר. Amar Rabbah
shtei teshuvot badavar. I got two responses to that. חדא, Chada, number
one, דחזינא לפומיה דינוקא דמלי חלב. d'chazina l'pumei d'yanuka d'malei chalav. Number
one, even when an infant never takes a break, when he finally
detaches, you see that his lips are all covered with milk. So
meaning even if he's not detaching himself, milk is still not all
going in, and therefore it is make the milk that does go
in considered susceptible. There's the- again, the milk that's going in is
considered food, the milk that doesn't go in is considered liquid, and
that you'll always have. Number one. ועוד, V'od, number two, מקום חלב
מעיין. makom chalav mayan. Forget it, forget this idea. It's like we
are treating it like this is something that's not part of the
woman, it's like it's some random food or liquid and she's coming
in contact with it and making it טמא. tamei. Right, that's how
we're conceptualizing this. You got it wrong. Something that comes from a
person's own sort of, you know, production of the body's own production
of liquids is naturally טמא. tamei. It's called a מעיין, ma'ayan, which
means a well, a well from within the person's body. Now let
me explain this תוספות's Tosafos way, which is just, you know, whatever,
a little clearer than רש"י's. Rashi The general principle that we're going
to see in a minute is that people that have a טומאה
tumah that is based on their body, like a יולדת yoledes or
a זבה zavah or a נידה niddah or a זב, zav, anybody
that has the טומאה tumah that's not about from the outside but
because of something that occurred to themselves, so the הלכה halacha is
that their מעיינות, ma'ayanos, their wellsprings, the liquids produced by their body
is an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. So a זב zav or a
זבה zavah or a נידה niddah is an אב הטומאה. av hatumah.
Their spit is also an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. Their blood is
also an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. It's not a ראשון. rishon. If
they touched liquid, they're an אב, av, the liquid would be a
ראשון. rishon. But because it is coming from one of these wellsprings
of the body, it is an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. Okay, that's
the principle. That now that doesn't apply to a woman who touched
somebody who touched a dead body. That's from the outside. But nevertheless
תוספות Tosafos is saying that we're assuming that rabbinically, since she's a
נידה niddah or יולדת, yoledes, so her liquids would be an אב
הטומאה, av hatumah, here too you don't need this idea like she
touched it and made it טמא tamei and did it come in
contact with liquid or not. The very fact that her body is
producing it and in other areas that is an אב הטומאה, av
hatumah, here as well at least it will be טמא tamei and
should make the infant טמא. tamei. You don't need to go through
this idea of touching and becoming הוכשר huchshar and so on. It's
coming from her body. Yes, it has to be טמא tamei first
or what is the for the milk to whatever? For the body's
production to be טמא? tamei? Yes. You mean let's say the body
produced it, let's say the woman became pregnant after she became a
נידה niddah and the milk was produced after? Yeah, it doesn't matter
when the stuff was produced in the body. Because in this example
she had to be טמא tamei first before that those liquids would
be considered... Yes, those liquids are טמא tamei when they come from
a טמא tamei person. From a טמא tamei person. Right. Okay. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so he says and
also מעיין הוא דקתני ma'ayan hu diktani because we have a משנה
Mishnah. we taught, a ברייתא Baraisa anyway, חלב אשה מטמא בין לרצון
בין שלא לרצון. chalav isha metamei bein leratzon bein shelo leratzon. The
milk of a woman is טמא tamei whether willfully or not willfully,
meaning and again we're assuming this idea of willful, if it were
an issue of coming in contact with a liquid, you would need
to want it to come in contact with a liquid and we're
saying regardless of whether you want it or not want it. בהמה
אינה מטמאה אלא לרצון. beheimah einah metamei ela leratzon. The milk of
an animal, that is just a normal law idea of like a
type of a food and therefore it needs to come in contact
with a liquid in order to be טמא, tamei, or you need
to want it. Okay, but anyway, but the case of the woman,
that because it doesn't matter whether you want it or not want
it, which shows that it's not in the normal category of this
idea of הכשר. hechshar. מאי לאו, mai lav, does this not mean
שלא לרצון דלא ניחא ליה? shelo leratzon delo nicha lei? It means
that you don't want it. וקתני מטמא, uktani metamei, and even if
the woman did not want the milk to come out of her
body, she's not interested in the milk, it still causes טומאה. tumah.
So again the principle here of רצון ratzon is when you're in
a category of things becoming susceptible, there's a relevant concept of wanting
them, wanting them to come in contact with liquid and so on.
If by the woman's milk that's not a relevant concept, it shows
that it's not about food becoming susceptible, it's a different category. And
רבא Rava says this different category is that it is her wellspring,
it is her own liquids from her own body and therefore it
doesn't need this whole idea. So now we're back to the question.
So this milk should be טמא, tamei, why is the infant not
טמא? tamei? So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא אמר רבא
היינו טעמא דתינוק טהור. ela amar Rava hainu ta'ama de-tinok tahor. Here's
the reason the תינוק tinok is טהור. tahor. ספק ינק שלא ינק.
safek yanok she-lo yanok. Remember how much food you have to eat
for your body to become טמא? tamei? You have to eat four
כביצים. kibeitzos. How often is it that an infant drinks that amount
of food? A, maybe he didn't even drink that amount of food.
ואם תמצא לומר ינק, ve-im timtza lomar yanok, and maybe he did
nurse that amount of milk, ספק ינק באכילת פרס ספק ינק ביותר
מכדי אכילת פרס. safek yanok b'achilas pras safek yanok b'yoser mik'dei achilas
pras. Maybe it took a lot more time. Okay, so it says
yeah, of course the milk is טמא. tamei. The reason we're saying
and that's why it says we're being lenient, we're allowing ourselves to
assume the infant is טהור tahor because we'll assume he didn't drink
enough and even if he did drink enough, he didn't do it
in enough time. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara is just going to
focus on this issue of do we apply this idea of a
מעיין, ma'ayan, of a liquids of a person to all liquids and
do we really apply it to the milk? So let's take a
look. ולרבא מקום חלב מעיין הוא? u'le-Rava makom chalav ma'ayan hu? Is
it really true that the milk is considered to come from like
a wellspring meaning that it has the status of, you know, fluids
from a person for this law of טומאה? tumah? ולא צריך הכשר?
ve-lo tzarich hechshar? And does not need to come in contact with
liquid? That's not what we taught in the משנה. mishnah, האשה שנטף
חלב מדדיה. ha-isha she-nataf chalav mi-dadeha. Let's say you have a woman
who is let's say a נידה niddah and milk drops from her
breast. ונפל לאוויר תנור venafal l'avir tanur and fell into an oven,
and an oven is a pottery oven that anything טמא tamei in
the space of a pottery oven makes everything טמא, tamei, so תנור
טמא, tanur tamei, it is טמא. tamei. Okay, that seems good, that
seems the idea that it is a liquid of a woman. וקשיא
לן דמאי כשר, v'kashya lan d'mai kashar, but when we taught that
משנה, Mishnah. we have a tradition that we ask, well how did
the milk come in contact, how does the milk become טמא? tamei?
What did it come, what liquid did it come in contact with?
ואמר רבי יוחנן בטיבו ולכלוכית על פי ידיה, v'amar Rabbi Yochanan b'tibu
v'luchluchis al pi yadeha, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said the same
thing we said before about the little drop that remained on the
breast. וכי, v'chi, so anyway you see that according to רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, milk of a from a נדה niddah is not considered
one of her, you know, fluids, and it's not an אב הטומאה,
av hatumah, and it's considered like something separate, and it needs to
come in contact and it needs to be susceptible and so on.
So וכי תימא רבא לא סבר לה כרבי יוחנן, v'chi teima Rava
lo savar lah k'Rabbi Yochanan, fine, that's רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, maybe
רבא Rava doesn't hold like רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. והתניא, v'hatanya, but
we have a ברייתא braisa that's more explicit. נמצאת אתה אומר תשעה
משקין בזב. nimtzas atah omer tisha mashkin b'zav. Okay, and here is
exactly the list of the fluids of a זב zav or a
זבה zavah or a נדה, niddah, which are considered to be the
fluids that are an אב הטומאה av hatumah and which are considered
not. And it basically says there are nine fluids, and there are
three categories of three each with different הלכות. halachos. Okay. הזיעה והליחה
סרוחה והרעי טהורין. hazeia v'leicha srucha v're'i tahorin. So basically sweat, sort
of, you know, sort of putrid, like a liquid, and and bowel
movements, you know, feces, assuming it's loose or something, all of those
because they're basically completely disgusting and not fit for anything, those are
completely טהור tahor even though they came from a person who's an
אב הטומאה. av hatumah. טהורין מכולם. tehorin mikulam. דמעת עינו, dima'as eino,
tears, ודם נגפתו, v'dam nigafto, blood from a wound, וחלב אישה, v'chalav
ishah, and milk of a woman, מטמאין טומאת משקין ברביעית. metamin tumas
mashkin b'revi'is. They are like normal liquids that these people came in
contact with. They're not this idea of מעיין, ma'ayan, they're not an
אב הטומאה, av hatumah, they're like normal liquids that you came in
contact with, and therefore they need a minimum amount, they need a
רביעית, revi'is, okay, and also for for drinking them, right, as when
you drink these טמא tamei liquids or eat these טמא tamei liquids
you become טמא, tamei, that's only רביעית, revi'is, anyway they're not considered
an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. What is considered an אב av when
it comes from a person who is an אב? av? רוקו, rokos,
spit, זובו, zovo, the flow, meaning, you know, if it is a
נדה niddah her blood flow, if it is a זב, zav, the
flow, his, you know, what's flow, you know, his penile flow, ומי
רגליו, u'mei raglav, and the urine. Those things מטמאין טומאה חמורה בכל
שהוא. metamin tumah chamurah b'chol shehu. Those things are considered an אב
הטומאה, av hatumah, that means the heavy one, it's an אב, av,
like the person himself or herself, and even the smallest amount. So
the upshot of all of this is that milk is in this
middle category. It's like a food, it's not like a primary טומאה.
tumah. ואם אמרת דמקום חלב מעיין חלב נמי נטמא טומאה חמורה בכל
שהוא כזובו ורוקו. v'im amarta d'makom chalav ma'ayan chalav nami nitma tumah
chamurah b'chol shehu k'zovo v'roko. So if you say that the that
the milk is considered a wellspring, the place where it comes from,
let it also be an אב הטומאה av hatumah בכל שהוא b'chol
shehu like the flow and the spit. אלא שמע מינה מקום חלב
אישה לאו מעיין הוא. ela shma mina makom chalav ishah lav ma'ayan
hu. You see רבא's Rava wrong, that it is not a wellspring
and therefore it is it is, you know, if it comes from
a woman who's a נדה, niddah, it is not an אב, av,
at most it's a ראשון, rishon, and therefore it's only when also
only when it becomes susceptible and comes in contact with a liquid.
Okay, so by the way, going back to the infant, it's still
a problem for the infant because of our what רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan explains, that the the milk on the breast is מכשיר machshir
the milk that comes out and into the infant's throat. So at
the end of the day, it's still the explanation why the infant
is not a problem is still רבא's Rava explanation, because maybe he
didn't drink enough and even if he drank enough not in enough
time, but the nature of the milk is seen as different. Now
the גמרא Gemara just does one last little check. אי הכי קשיא
המתניתא דאמר רבא מטמא בין לרצון ובין שלא לרצון. iy hachi kashya
hamasnisa d'amar Rava metamei bein l'ratzon u'vein shelo l'ratzon. Remember we quoted
a ברייתא braisa that said that the milk from a woman is
טמא tamei whether you want it or not, and normally when we
speak about having things become susceptible and come in contact with liquid,
it's only when you want it. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
מי סברת שלא לרצון דאמר דלא ניחא ליה. mi savras shelo l'ratzon
d'amar d'lo nicha lei. שלא לרצון shelo l'ratzon doesn't mean that you
don't want that milk. לא מאי שלא לרצון? lo mai shelo l'ratzon?
What does שלא לרצון shelo l'ratzon mean? So they add a line,
a word here that makes it better. מאי שלא לרצון בסתמא, mai
shelo l'ratzon bistama, you didn't, you didn't actively want it. If you
actively didn't want it, it does not become susceptible for טומאה. tumah.
But you didn't actively want it. דאמר דדעתיה דתינוק קריבה לגבי חלב.
d'amar d'daiteih d'tinok krevah legabei chalav. So even if you don't actively
want it, we still assume look, your infant wants the milk, and
that's enough to say that it's desired. אבל אמר לא ניחא ליה,
aval amar lo nicha lei, if you said explicitly you don't want
it, טהור, tahor, then it's טהור. tahor. So that was a little
digression into working out whether milk is or is not, but the
basic point is milk can become טמא, tamei, and the reason the
infant is not טמא tamei is because of this ספק ספיקא. sfeik
sfeika. Yes. The child saying that it is, or infant? No, so
תוספות Tosafos says it's not what the infant wants, it's what the
mother wants for the infant. Okay, let's keep on going. אכל אוכלין
טמאים. achal ochlin tmeiyin. Now the משנה Mishnah. *mishna* goes back to
the משנה Mishnah *mishna* that says if you ate טמא tamei *tamei*
things it combines to make you טמא tamei, *tamei*. למה לי שהי
דקתני ושהה *Lama li shehi dkatani vshahah*? Why does it say you
wait? Because the משנה Mishnah, *mishna* sounded like if you ate this
טמא tamei *tamei* stuff and then went into the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash* and waited in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash? *Beit
HaMikdash*, like where it phrased, it talked about waiting, it used waiting
after it says you went into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit
HaMikdash*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is just clarifying that. No, אמר
רב Amar Rav: יהודה הכי תני *Amar Rav Yehuda hachi tani*, this
is what it means. אכל אוכלין טמאים ושתה משקין טמאים *Achal ochlin
tme'in vshata mashkin tme'in*, if you ate or drank טמא tamei. *tamei*
food, ושתה רביעית revi'it, יין *vshata revit yayin*, or you drank a
רביעית revi'it *revit* of wine and it's instead of being drunk, then
here's where you have to insert the phrase you waited. ושהה באכילתן
ובשתייתן כדי אכילת פרס *Vshahah bachilatan uvshiyatatn kedei achilat pras*, only if
the process of, פרס פרס *pras pras*, the process of eating or
drinking was not more than a פרס *pras*, then you're considered טמא
*tamei* or then you're considered drunk, and then ונכנס למקדש חייב chayav
*venichnas lamikdash chayav*, then if you enter into the בית המקדש *Beit
HaMikdash* you will have transgressed. Okay, so the waiting is referring to
the process of eating, not to the going into the בית המקדש
*Beit HaMikdash*. So again, what's interesting is that we use the amount
of a פרס *pras*, not just for כזית *kezayit*, but even eating
טמא *tamei* food, which is four כזיתים *kezayitim*, even that is limited
to the time of a פרס *pras*, and even by a רביעית
revi'it, *revit*, which is a liquid, we use the amount that it
takes to eat a פרס *pras*. So that becomes the standard almost
regardless of the case. Now we end this discussion with a fascinating
discussion about this law of not being טמא *tamei* and entering into
the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, right? It's a פסוק *pasuk* in the
תורה *Torah*, יין ושכר אל תשת אתה ובניך אתך בבאכם אל אהל
מועד ולא תמותו *Yayin vshichar al tesht atah uvaneycha itach bevochem el
ohel moed velo tamutu*, right, right after בני אהרן *Bnei Aharon* about
נדב ואביהוא *Nadav v'Avihu*, which is why, you know, חז"ל *Chazal* understand
that one of the reasons they might have died is because they
were drunk when they entered into the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. And
משה *Moshe* says, you know, יין ושכר אל תשת *yayin vshichar al
tesht*, when you go in or else you will die. Okay, so
that's what we learn, that you're חייב chayav. מיתה misa, *chayav mita*,
not by a court, but בידי שמים *bidei shamayim*, if you enter
drunk into the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. And here the question is,
what defines drunk? Our משנה *mishna* said a רביעית *revit*, but we
had an opinion that if you added a little water or took
a little bit of a break, it would not be drunk. Let's
take a look. רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*, תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan: *Tanu
rabanan*, יין ושכר אל תשת *Yayin vshichar al tesht*, you shall not
drink wine or intoxicating liquid. So, יכול אפילו כל שהוא *Yachol afilu
kol shehu*, maybe even a tiny bit you'll transgress? אפילו מגיתו *Afilu
migito*, or even if it is wine straight out of the pressing
vat, meaning basically grape juice? יין מגיתו *Yayin migito* is grape juice,
it hasn't yet fermented. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar: ושכר *Talmud lomar vshichar*.
No, ושכר *vshichar* qualifies what type of wine. אין אסור אלא כדי
לשכר *Ein assur ela kedei lshaker*, only as much wine that will
make you drunk, which means number one, it has to have fermented
and be alcoholic, and number two, it has to be a minimum
amount. וכמה כדי לשכר רביעית יין *Vchama kedei lshaker revit yayin*, it
has to be a רביעית *revit* of wine, three and a half
ounces, okay, which is pretty little. בן ארבעים יום *Ben arbaim yom*,
and it has at least have fermented for forty days. אם כן
מה תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar: יין *Im ken mah talmud lomar yayin*?
So why does it say יין *yayin*? If it's all about becoming
drunk? לומר לך שמוזהרין עליו בכל שהוא *Lomar lach shemuharin alav bechol
shehu*, ומוזהרין עליו מגיתו *umuharin alav migito*. You transgress if you drink
any amount of wine. If you drink even a tiny bit, even
if you essentially drink grape juice, you transgress, but you're not חייב
מיתה *chayav mita* unless it is wine that can make you drunk,
unless it is fermented and a רביעית *revit*. So there's two levels:
one is to transgress, the other is to be חייב מיתה *chayav
mita*. Okay, I should by the way also point out that it
seems like this תנא *tanna* is reading the ו *vav* as not
as two separate things but as a hybrid. And sometimes you have
this, I forget there's a technical term for this, when a ו
*vav* really is a hyphen. For example, when אברהם *Avraham* says גר
ותושב אנכי עמכם *Ger vtoshav anochi imachem*. That's normally translated as a
resident alien. Not I am both a, you know, an alien and
a resident. No, I am a hybrid, I'm a resident alien. So
יין ושכר *yayin vshichar* is being read here as intoxicating wine. Not
two things, but one thing: intoxicating wine. And but he does say
that less than that you transgress, you're just not חייב מיתה *chayav
mita*. That's opinion number one. Now we go on. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda, אומר יין *Rabbi Yehuda omer yayin*. אין לי אלא יין *Ein
li ela yayin*, I only know wine. שאר משקין משכרין מנין *She'ar
mashkin meshakrin minayin*? How about other intoxicating liquids? תלמוד לומר ושכר *Talmud
lomar vshichar*. So he's not reading it as a hybrid, he's reading
it as two things. Wine you transgress, and intoxicating beverage you transgress,
alcohol, liquor you transgress. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר יין *Im ken
mah talmud lomar yayin*? So what's the emphasis of wine? על היין
במיתה ועל שאר משקין באזהרה *Al hayayin bemita veal she'ar mashkin be'azhara*.
He also has two tiers, but his two tiers is not intoxicating
wine versus non-intoxicating wine, his two tiers is wine versus other, other,
you know, intoxicating beverages, intoxicating liquids. That's his, that he says that
you can transgress without wine, but not חייב מיתה *chayav mita*. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer*, יין אל תשת ושכר אל
תשת *Yayin al tesht vshichar al tesht*, כדרך שכרותו *kederech shichruto*. That
don't, he says that don't drink wine and don't drink it, and
presumably don't drink it, what does ושכר *vshichar* mean? The way you
cannot drink wine is the way in which it will get you
drunk. הא אם הפסיק בו או שנתן לתוכו מים כל שהוא פטור
patur, *Ha im hifsik bo o shenatan letocho mayim kol shehu patur*.
If you took a break or you added some water, you're exempt.
So meaning this seems like the first opinion that ושכר *vshichar* is
read as a, as a hybrid: don't drink intoxicating. taking wine, but
rather than qualifying the type of wine, it has to be fermented,
it has to be a certain amount, what it also qualifies is
how you drink it. Don't drink it in an intoxicating way. If
you take a break or have some liquid, the water into it,
then it's not considered drinking it in an intoxicating way. במאי פליגי?
What's the debate about? תנא קמא סבר גמרינן שכר שכר מנזיר. Tanna
kamma savar gamrinan sheichar sheichar mi-nazir. We learn the word שכר sheichar
intoxicating from a נזיר. nazir. And by a נזיר, nazir, it's only
about wine. So here too, even though it has the word intoxicating,
it qualifies wine, but it is not something independent. רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, who says other drinks as well, לא ילפינן שכר שכר מנזיר.
lo yalfinan sheichar sheichar mi-nazir. He doesn't learn it fine. So he
treats it separate, liquor as well. רבי אליעזר סבר, Rabbi Eliezer savar,
מה שכר מידי דמשכר, ma sheichar midi de-meshaker, that שכר sheichar means
in a way that gets you drunk. So here too, you have
to drink it in a way that gets you drunk. Okay. כמאן
אזלא הא דתניא? ke-man azla ha de-tanya? Who is this going like
the ברייתא? braita? אכל דבילה קעלית. achal deveilah ke-ilit. If you eat
this type of a pressed date, which of a certain place of
קעלית, Ke-ilit, ושתה דבש ve-shata devash or you drank honey, presumably that
might mean like mead, right? Mead was made from honey, I believe.
או חלב o chalav or milk, ונכנס למקדש ושימש ve-nichnas la-mikdash ve-shimesh
and you went into the בית המקדש and you did an עבודה.
avodah. That's another question. Are you only חייב if you do an
עבודה avodah or just for going into the בית המקדש? Presumably it's
if you did an עבודה, avodah, then לוקה lokei or you get
lashes or some say חייב. Okay, you transgress. Okay, so here now
the גמרא Gemara, assumes that these things will make you drunk. I
mean, to say milk will make you drunk, yeah, I don't know.
Anyway, כמאן, ke-man, it might also have to do with also with
יעל Yael and סיסרא Sisera and she drank, made him drink some
milk and he fell asleep, so maybe associates falling asleep with milk,
I don't know. Anyway, point is that these are things that are
certainly not wine and you could still transgress. Who is that going
like? כמאן כרבי יהודה? ke-man ke-Rabbi Yehuda? Like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda
fine, who says it's not limited to wine and part of the
חידוש chiddush is it's not even limited to liquids. Anything that makes
you drunk. Okay, but you don't get מיתה, you only get the
prohibition. אמר רב יהודה בר חוסאי, amar Rav Yehuda bar Chusai, so
רב יהודה בר חוסאי Rav Yehuda bar Chusai said, הלכה כרבי אליעזר.
halacha ke-Rabbi Eliezer. We rule like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, that it
is if you add a little bit of water or you take
a break, that is enough. Now that's if you drink a רביעית,
right? What happens if you drink ten gallons? That might be a
different story. Okay, but if you only are drinking a רביעית and
you added some water or took a break, then you're off the
hook. Yeah. He said פטור, does that mean that it's actually מותר?
mutar? No, right, presumably not. Okay. וקרי רב עליה דרבי אליעזר, ve-kari
Rav aleih de-Rabbi Eliezer, רב Rav said regarding רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer.
טובינא דחכימי, tuvina de-chakimei, the sort of best of the sages or
a great one of the sages. All right. רב אחא מהוצא, Rav
Acha mi-Hutza, now going to have one or two cases. הוי נדרא
עלה דדביתהו. havei nidra ala de-deviteihu. So his wife, he had basically,
for not clear who made the נדר, neder, but anyway, he let's
say had vowed that his wife is forbidden in benefit to him,
which is a little problematic. So he had to get that vow
annulled. אזל לקמיה דרב אשי. azal le-kamei de-Rav Ashi. He went to
רב אשי Rav Ashi to get the vow annulled. אמר ליה, amar
lei, so רב אשי Rav Ashi said to him, זיל האידנא ותא
למחר. zil idna ve-ta le-machar. Go today, come back tomorrow. Why? Why
can't I see you today? דרב לא מוקי אמורא עליה מיומא טבא
לחבריה. de-Rav lo moki amora aleih mi-yoma tava le-chavreih. רב Rav did
not have, would not have an אמורא. amora. The אמורא amora was
the person that would teach, you know, the rabbi would, the real
אמורא, amora, the real sage would sort of, he'd be the loudspeaker,
would like whisper the things to this אמורא amora and the אמורא
amora would project it to the whole crowd. So when you say
מוקי אמורא עליה, moki amora aleih, have an אמורא amora standing by
you, it basically means, you know, that you are going to give
your שיעור, shiur, teach the masses. So רב Rav would not do
this if it were like two days of יום טוב, Yom Tov,
meaning let's say two days of חול המועד Chol HaMoed or whatever
it might be, two days of יום טוב. Yom Tov. Why would
he not do it? Because, you know, if he had just had
a nice meal and had some wine with it, he'd be afraid
that he would be a little drunk. And when you're drunk, not
only are you not allowed to go into the בית המקדש and
do an עבודה, avodah, but it says ולהורות את בני ישראל. u-le-horot
et benei Yisrael. At the end of that thing is you can
also not give הוראה, hora'ah, give instruction, teach. So therefore, רב Rav
would not do this משום שכרות mishum shichrut because he'd be afraid
he'd be drunk. So presumably he was saying the same thing, I
had some wine today, I'm not going to give you a פסק
הלכה, psak halacha, come tomorrow and I will give you a פסק
הלכה psak halacha then. Okay. אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said
to him, והאמר רב הלכה כרבי אליעזר? ve-ha-amar Rav halacha ke-Rabbi Eliezer?
One minute, רב Rav said the הלכה halacha like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer We said that before. And רבי אליעזר said if you did
it, you took a little break or you didn't do it all
at one time, it's not a problem. So presumably that applies in
this case. ומר הוא דקא רמי ביה מיא, u-mar hu de-ka rami
beih maya, and you put water in your wine, so it shouldn't
be an issue. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him,
הא לא קשיא. ha lo kashya. That's not difficult. הא ברביעית הא
ביותר מרביעית. ha be-revi'it ha be-yoter mi-revi'it. Like I said before, if
it's a lot of wine, more than a רביעית, a little, now
of course exactly at which stage, let's say it's a lot of
water and a lot of wine, how much of the lot of
wine? Okay, but not all things will this water or break get
you off if you really get drunk, it's a problem. And of
course you realize, I hope you realize the irony of all of
this. What's the irony of all of this? They're having a halakhic
discussion. Why, why? I can't give you a halakhic answer about this.
No, no, but what about this? What about that? Here's why I
can't give הלכה, halacha, here's this הלכה. halacha. So they're having a
halakhic discussion. But maybe since the point is it's not a halakhic
discussion that he's going to act on, it's just telling him why
I'm not acting, even though in the end you're talking הלכה, halacha,
but for the person who's asking it's more theoretical. Actually, actually, somebody
told me a similar story that he was like shaving or something
was חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, whatever the case was anyway, and someone
was also there in the bathroom, you know, and said to him,
oh, you know, you're not allowed to do this, what you're doing.
And he said back, you're not allowed to tell me הלכה halacha
in the bathroom. Anyway, but okay, moving on. Anyway, okay. So now
let's get up to the משנה. We'll do a few more minutes.
Okay. תנו רבנן: Rabbanan, ולהבדיל בין הקדש ובין החול. U'lehavdil bein hakodesh
u'vein hachol. So this is part of what you're not allowed to
do when you're drunk, to distinguish between holy and profane, so like
to give a פסק הלכה. psak halacha. Like you can't. You can't,
right. אלו: Elu: so what's קדש וחול? kodesh v'chol? אלו דמים וערכין
חרמים והקדשות. Elu damim v'erchin charamim v'hekdeshos. To assess, remember like all
we've been learning about now, somebody makes ערכין, erchin, חרמים, charamim, הקדש.
hekdesh. So one of the כהן's Kohen jobs is to assess how
much it's worth to allow it to be redeemed. So even that
type of an assessment, which requires a clear head, although it's just
about money, you cannot do. בין הטמא ובין הטהור. Bein hatamei u'vein
hatahor. אלו טומאות וטהרות. Elu tumos v'taharos. Okay, you can't distinguish, you
can't give a ruling if something is טמא or טהור. tahor. ולהורות,
U'lehoros, or to give or to give instruction. זו הוראה. Zu hora'ah.
This is what we would normally call halakhic rulings. You can't give
halakhic rulings. את כל החוקים, Es kol hachukim, all the laws. אלו
מדרשות. Elu midrashos. That is a, which is interesting, מדרש, midrash, which
you would think means it's not really law, that's a little bit
strange why that's included. רש"י Rashi says, שדורשים בפירקא, she'dorshim b'pirka, right,
it's not exactly clear. Anyway, so, you know, why that, what, that
is not, you know, that's just דרשה, drasha, that's not really law,
why that's included. אשר דבר ה', Asher diber Hashem, that God has
spoken. זו הלכה. Zu halacha. So that's being straight הלכה. halacha. Presumably
the difference between הלכה halacha and הוראה hora'ah is that הוראה hora'ah
is when it requires me to figure out something new. הלכה, halacha,
הלכה halacha is to give like a straight ruling. Okay, so like
it's just black letter law and you're just passing it over. Presumably
even that is forbidden. ביד משה, B'yad Moshe, through the hand of
Moshe. זה תלמוד. Zeh Talmud. That's more what we're doing, analysis. Okay,
so, יכול אף המשנה? yakhol af haMishnah? Maybe you can't even do
משנה. משנה is like straight, you know, statements and they're not even
to be applied in practice, right? It's just רבי יהודה says this,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that. So maybe you can't even do
that. תלמוד לומר: ולהורות. u'lehoros. There has to be an aspect of
judgment, okay, which also raises then the question of why הלכה halacha
can't be done. But anyway, something that requires a certain amount of
discerning and judgment and some type of פסק הלכה. psak halacha. Maybe
הוראה hora'ah can mean either judgment or הלכה, halacha, but something that
is neither, like משנה, which is just repetition of tradition and it's
not about הלכה, halacha, that is not a problem. Okay, which also
goes back and raises the question how they could have a discussion
about whether they could פסקן, pasken, even if it was more theoretical,
we're seeing here as well that some theoretical things are also forbidden.
Anyway, just to end up, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda omer: יכול אף תלמוד? yakhol af Talmud? So he then
is going to question the idea of learning גמרא, Gemara. like analysis.
That, תלמוד לומר: ולהורות. u'lehoros. No, he says it's not everything that
requires judgment. There has to be a הלכה, halacha, an application. So
having the type of learning that's done without yet bringing it to
bottom line application, that is not a problem. גמרא אזלא הא דתניא:
Gemara azla ha d'tanya: it's going like what we taught in the
ברייתא. Baraita. יצא שרץ טמא וצפרדע טהור. Yatza sheretz tamei v'tzfardea tahor.
If to say that, for example, this שרץ sheretz is טמא, this
צפרדע tzfardea is טהור. tahor. Of course, I'm not sure that everybody
knows which rodents are טמא or not, but let's say, let's translate
it in terms we know. To say, let's say, that חזיר chazir
is טמא. How do you know that that's not a problem? ששתויי
יין מורים בהם. She'shisuy yayin morim bahem. הוראה. Hora'ah. That you can
give a ruling on something that's blatantly obvious. So נימא neima רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה? Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda? He, maybe that's רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda that excludes certain things. So, you
know, ולא רבנן, v'lo Rabbanan, not the Rabbis, because maybe the Rabbis
are saying that anything that has any quality of הלכה halacha to
it or any analysis to it is a problem. No, אפילו תימא
afilu teima רבנן, even the Rabbis. ושני הכא דזיל קרי בי רב.
V'shani hacha d'zil krei bei rav. Here go ask, you know, you
go ask a kindergartner these questions. So there's some things that are
so blatantly obvious that it's not considered to even be doing anything
of significance to make those statements. Exactly כשר. kosher. Right, exactly. Okay.
אמר רב: Rav, הלכה כרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. halacha k'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda. We rule like רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda,
which means that if you're drunk, you could still learn גמרא. Gemara
והא רב לא מוקים אמורא מיומא טבא לחבריה משום שכרות? V'ha Rav
lo mukim amora miyoma tava l'chavrei mishum shikhrus? What do you mean?
רב, Rav we just got through saying that רב Rav, did not
give a שיעור shiur from one יום טוב Yom Tov to the
next, meaning like one day of יום טוב Yom Tov to the
next day of יום טוב, Yom Tov, because he was a little
drunk. Why not give your גמרא Gemara שיעור? shiur? You just said
you're allowed to give a גמרא Gemara שיעור shiur when you're drunk.
So גמרא says: שאני רב דאורי מורי. shani Rav d'orei morei. So
רב, Rav that's different, when רב Rav gives a שיעור... shiur... Why
not give your שיעור shiur without פוסק'נינג paskening הלכה, halacha, so that
we're only talking theoretical today, we're not going to פוסק? pasken? No.
כל היכא דיתיב רב, kol heicha deyativ Rav, whenever רב is sitting,
לא סגי ליה בלא הוראה. lo sagi lei belo hora'ah. He can't
get out of פוסק'נינג. paskening. Either his natural inclination or people are
going to ask for an answer. It's not possible for him to
give a שיעור shiur without having to give some פסק הלכה psak
halacha in it, and therefore he would not do it. But again,
although it talked more about theoretical, in the end the upshot is
that what's really a problem is פסק הלכה. psak halacha.